So today's דף, daf, we finish the פרק. perek. It's דף daf
ס"א samech-aleph 61 and we are finishing discussing cases about situations that
make
the
problematic wine. Most of the conversation until now has been different types
of touch and I've pointed out that there has been like not
so much of a systematic treatment in the גמרא, Gemara, a lot
of sort of different
cases and at the end we'll try to sort of bring some
of that together. And this last משנה mishna though deals with the
case of wine that is owned by or under the somewhat auspices
of a non-Jew because until now we've been dealing with wine that's
owned by Jews and how you know when the non-Jew touches it
in different ways. So let's take a look at that and there's
interesting question about whether that's a conceptually distinct category or not. So
the משנה mishna says as follows:
המטהר יינו של עובדי כוכבים. Hametaher yeino shel ovdei kochavim. Somebody is
coming to purify the wine of the non-Jew. I want to repeat
now before we get into the details, point I made at the
end of yesterday which I think is very important, which is the
use of the phrase מטהר, metaher, to purify. Because the opposite of
מטהר metaher is טמא, tamei, that it's impure. And what is striking
and you know this goes to question right through you were asking
about you know does this lead to constantly thinking about עבודה זרה.
avoda zara. What's striking is is that what becomes very much the
dominant sort of framing
lens or if you would sort of parallel category that's used to
think about this is טומאה, tumah, impurity. And if you think about
it for a minute there's a reason because impurity, classic impurity is
what? The impure thing touches something and communicates its impurity through touch
and to some degree you know sort of contaminates, invalidates that other
thing. Well what do you have by wine? You've got this Jewish
wine touched by a non-Jew and now that touch makes it invalid.
And that was really brought up at the end of you know
yesterday where it made this whole analogy to the same way a
זב, zav, you know different ways the זב zav touches something directly
or indirectly, a non-Jew touches directly or indirectly also makes it טמא.
tamei. So the touch of a non-Jew is like the touch of
a זב. zav. But you had it before in defining what type
of you know how you think about the object, are you think
about the touch when it's something is being poured is it one
unit or two units, right? If you touch the side of the
barrel through the hole and all of those are borrowed from the
world of טומאה וטהרה. tumah v'taharah. Now so and it's one thing
to say okay there's certain analogies we need to borrow that but
here you actually get that it's not just an analogy to help
us sort of think about it legally but it actually becomes part
of the whole way we we you know sort of articulate what
this is about like you know the concept מטהר. metaher. And remember
that non-Jews were treated as טמא. tamei. The rabbis considered non-Jews טמא
tamei and they made them זבים zavim ונידות niddos and treated them
as such. So here what you have is that טומאה tumah which
is no longer really relevant in a world that doesn't really care
so much
about קודשים kodshim וטהרות taharos and so on I mean in the
Tannaic period they did more but all of a sudden where that
plays out if you would the טומאה tumah of non-Jews is when
is their touching of the wine. So I would actually say that
you know psychologically, religiously psychologically, the attitude of wine does not so
much anymore get experienced as it's about עבודה זרה, avoda zara, it
gets experienced as the touch of non-Jews you know contaminates and it
thinks more sort of of טומאה וטהרה tumah v'taharah categories. So I
think that that's really worth noting is how much that becomes almost
the you know metaphor, the discourse to talk about it. So the
משנה mishna here is המטהר יינו של עובדי כוכבים, hametaher yeino shel
ovdei kochavim, if you're coming to purify the wine. You're coming to
take the wine of non-Jews and make it wine that's kosher and
could be sold to Jews without the non-Jew's ownership or possible touch
perhaps contaminating it and making it יין נסך. yayin nesech. So how
are you going to do that? Okay so let's take a look.
ונותנו ברשותו, V'nosno birshuso, so you actually are processing this whole wine
for the non-Jew. He is not touching it, he owns it, but
he's staying away and you go ahead and you place it, so
you've taken the grapes, you've pressed them, you've got the wine into
the barrels, and now afterwards you take those barrels of wine and
you put them into the רשות, reshus, into the you know sort
of property of the non-Jew. ובבית פתוח לרשות הרבים, Ub'bayis patuach lirshus
harabbim,
but at least the house that they're being stored in is open
to the public domain. בעיר שיש בה עובדי כוכבים וישראלים, B'ir sheyesh
ba ovdei kochavim v'yisraelim, and it's a city that has Jews and
non-Jews. Now as you see once again we have a huge תוספות,
Tosfos, it's a debate with רש"י, Rashi, I'm going to explain it
תוספות's Tosfos way which is a better explanation I should say by
the way that תוספות Tosfos you know here refers to in רש"י's
Rashi sort of last version of his commentary he explained it this
way and he asks a lot of questions and
then...
So it was really like a lot of complicated trying to sort
of figure out exactly what the dominant principles were and how to
explain the specific cases. So what does תוספות Tosafos say? That the
case is that the Jew has the lock of to the house.
He has the key to the house, although it's the non-Jew's house,
he's got the key, and he also puts some type of seal
on the door that if you were to open the door, you
would see that the seal's been ruptured, or a seal on the
barrels. מפתח וחותם ביד ביד ישראל. Maftaye'ach v'chosam b'yad b'yad Yisrael.
That'll be a thing we will see in the גמרא. Gemara. So
therefore, I the non-Jew owns the wine, I've but the grapes in
the vineyard and everything, but I've processed it, made it into wine,
he hasn't been around. Now I'm storing it in his house. So
since he owns it, he might feel comfortable to walk into the
house and when nobody is looking, do a little sprinkling to עבודה
זרה. Avodah Zarah. But ah, I have the lock and key and
I have the seal. So do I have to be afraid that
he is going to do that anyway since he's the owner? So
it says, if it is an עיר, ir, if it is the
house is exposed to the public domain, and it's an עיר שיש
בה עובדי כוכבים וישראלים ir she'yesh ba ovdei kochavim v'yisraelim and there
are Jews and non-Jews that go through the public domain and are
in the city. So then it is מותר, mutar, it is permissible.
Why? Because people are going to see him there by the front
door trying to pick the lock, right, and trying to sneak in.
So the fact that it's locked and sealed, although not mentioned in
the משנה, Mishnah, means that and he doesn't have that means that
he will not be trying to break into the house if there
are other Jews possibly around that will see it and he'll look
suspicious. בעיר שכולה עובדי כוכבים אסור, B'ir she'kulo ovdei kochavim assur, but
if it's all non-Jews, then it's forbidden. Of course, you know, non-Jews
would also be presumably concerned that they see somebody trying to pick
a lock and go into a house, but I don't know, maybe
they would understand the context as, oh, he's probably just trying to
take the non-Jew to take the Jew's wine and they'd ignore it.
So anyway, at least in that case, if it was all non-Jews,
and we don't have any presence there, we have to be concerned.
עד שישב ומשמר, Ad she'yeishev um'shamer,
until you have a Jew that is present and watching, you know,
and making sure that nobody breaks into the house. ואינו שומר צריך
ליהשב ומשמר, V'eino shomer tzarich l'yeishev um'shamer,
although we just said until you sit and watch, you don't have
to constantly be sitting there and watching. אף על פי שהוא יוצא
ונכנס מותר, Af al pi she'hu yotzei v'nichnas mutar, even if you,
you know, periodically drop by it's permissible, very important משנה Mishnah brought
down in the beginning of מסכת חולין Masechet Chullin to discuss that
type of השגחה, hashgachah, a השגחה hashgachah called a יוצא ונכנס, yotzei
v'nichnas, which is is that even if you're not always present, if
you are periodically dropping by and making surprise visits and the person
doesn't know when, that's enough to keep people honest. Okay, so therefore,
again, the assumption is that the house is locked, somebody would look
furtive and sneaky if they would try to be picking the lock,
even the non-Jewish person who technically owns the house and the wine,
and therefore it's okay if it's exposed to Jewish passersby or somebody
is periodically checking up. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר רשות עובדי כוכבים
אחת היא. Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer reshus ovdei kochavim achasi. No,
non-Jews, it's all
one domain. Idol worshippers. Well, thank you, but the reason I actually
say non-Jews is because pretty much every single time in the משנה,
Mishnah, עובדי כוכבים ovdei kochavim is not the original text of the
משנה. Mishnah. It was the, yeah, it was the self-censored text so
that we could tell the non-Jews that we're not referring to them,
we were only referring to the ancient pagans, but the original text
actually was נוכרי. nochri.
So, but all of our texts have already been
censored. So anyway, all of the domains of the non-Jews are one.
Now what does that mean and how is that relevant? The גמרא
Gemara will explain that, okay? But that's principle number one, that if
the non-Jew owns it, and he might feel too comfortable getting access
to it, even though you're trying to give it a הכשר hechsher
of kosher wine. So as long as you keep it locked and
there are people you know that that would see somebody trying to
break in, that's okay. You have a question?
Yes, המטהר יינו של עובדי כוכבים. ham'taher yeino shel ovdei kochavim. Yes.
In fact, the case that you posited, it isn't wine when the
Jew takes possession. Right, and maybe it's not even טמא tamei when
the Jew takes possession.
Right, you're not really מטהר, m'taher, you're preventing it from becoming טמא.
tamei. You're absolutely correct. So, מטהר, m'taher, right, once the non-Jew makes
it סתם יינם stam yeinam there's no way to be מטהר m'taher
it. Right.
The claim of the משנה Mishnah is is seems exaggerated in the
first words.
Yes, I would totally agree with that.
And it's funny that the whole discussion about the process leading before
it became wine is not even being discussed, but maybe that's exactly
sort of what's implicit, that the only way you can produce this
wine is that you kept him away while it was being made,
but now the question is how do you continue? But you're right,
I agree the phrase is misleading. Okay, let's look, and I want
to talk about that a little bit more in the in terms
of the next case. So let's look at the next case: המטהר
יינו של עובדי כוכבים ונתנו ברשותו. ham'taher yeino shel ovdei kochavim v'nosno
birshuso.
So again, you have the wine of the non-Jew and you give
it put but after you've made this wine, made it בכשרות, be'kashrus,
you now are storing it in his
his house. Okay, but what do you have that makes it better
without the door being locked and sealed? והלה כותב לו התקבלתי ממך
מעות Vehala kotev lo hitkabalti mimcha maot and he says, he writes
to you a receipt, it might even be a receipt prior to
it actually being true, but he writes to you a receipt which
just says you've already paid me for it. Which is essentially saying
it's basically yours now. Now that might again be a prior receipt
to actually having been paid, the Jew now has to sell the
wine, get the money, pay the non-Jew, but because the non-Jew has
written this receipt, it's like he recognizes that this is now the
Jew's wine. He owes me money for it, but it's now the
Jew's wine. And because now it is fully owned by the Jew,
he's going to be a little more reluctant to go ahead and
do something wrong. ממך מעות מותר, mimcha maot mutar, then it's permissible.
אבל אם רוצה ישראל להוציא ואינו מניחו עד שייתן לו את מעותיו,
Aval im rotze Yisrael lehotzi veeino manicho ad sheyiten lo et meotav,
but if he has not given it over to the total control
of the Jew, and if the Jew wants to go ahead and
now take this wine out of the house and bring it to
his storage facility, start selling, and he says, you got to pay
me before you're going to start doing anything,
then זה היה מעשה בבית שאן ואסרו. ze haya maase beVeis She'an
ve'asru. This was a story in בית שאן Beis She'an and they
forbade it, because this would be a case where the non-Jew feels
that it's you know, that it's not—he still has control over it,
it's basically still his wine. The Jew doesn't have control over it
and it's in his house and it's not like it's being locked
up like the first case. So this is a case where it
is a problem. Now I want to say something about this, what
רש״י Rashi does and תוספות Tosafos argues on, because you know תוספות
Tosafos's read is much better. But what רש״י Rashi does is he
conflates the two cases of the משנה Mishnah and he basically says
you need both. You need both that it's you know, the house
is exposed to a רשות הרבים reshus harabim and people will walk
by and see and the guy can't get away with it, and
that it's like the Jew already owns it, that the non-Jew writes
the receipt. And the logic for this is, and this is important
when you have a different conceptual category, is תוספות Tosafos says this
explicitly in quoting רש״י, Rashi, הוי כיינו של ישראל havei keyeino shel
Yisrael
because you know, there's a question, I've been saying all along and
it's really based on the רמב״ם Rambam and or on רש״י Rashi's
read, that if it's the non-Jew's wine, then it's almost like—the way
the רמב״ם Rambam phrases it like this: wine that's owned by non-Jews
is סתם יינם stam yeinam and you assume it's a problem. Wine
that's owned by Jews you have to know, was there an event
that maybe it was touched and and and and you start worrying
about what type of touch and how it was touched or whatever.
So, but conceptually if it's non-Jew's wine, it's almost we assume it
was touched and we don't even care about the circumstances. So רש״י
Rashi basically works with those conceptual categories and he says the way
you can be מטהר יינו metaher yeino is by not making—is by
making it not יינו, yeino, is by making it, you know, as
if it were the Jew's wine and by therefore like you know,
the Jew is the virtual owner of it. But as soon as
it's the non-Jew's wine, we basically start with an assumption that it's
a problem.
תוספות Tosafos does not read it that way. תוספות Tosafos says in
the first case, you did not pay for it yet, the non-Jew
completely owns it, and it's not a different case—different category, it's just
if he feels you know, too much at liberty and too much
that he's an owner and a בעל הבית baal habayis and all
those things, then there's obviously a higher level of concern that he
might have touched it. But for תוספות Tosafos really there's one category:
You've got wine, what's the likelihood the non-Jew touched it? So if
the non-Jew owns it, the likelihood is a lot higher and you
need a lot more safeguards; if the Jew owns it, the likelihood
is less. But that is basically not a distinct category. For רש״י
Rashi and it seems like for the רמב״ם, Rambam, it's important to
conceptually try to make this Jewish wine; non-Jewish wine is more fundamentally
a problem.
What it sounds like using modern terminology is that we're looking at
the distinction between a case where a Jew has a license
to
produce wine from the grapes of a non-Jew and take consignment of
it but it's still owned by the non-Jew up until the point
that he makes good on the final payment.
I couldn't have said it better, but yeah.
The second case is where he actually is taking title to it
and having a debt against it.
Right, absolutely correct. Great. Okay, thank you. Very very articulately said. So
let's take a look now at the גמרא. Gemara. We're going to
work with תוספות Tosafos's reading that even you can even have a
case where it's totally the non-Jew's,
but still with enough protections and a locked house you're okay. So
let's see what the גמרא Gemara says about this. First case: בעיר
שכולה עובדי כוכבים נמי? Be'ir shekula ovdei kochavim nami?
So the גמרא Gemara says even in a city that's that's all
non-Jews, if you've got—again this is how תוספות Tosafos reads it, if
the house is locked and sealed, that should be enough. So the—I'm
sorry, I'm sorry. The גמרא Gemara says if the house—so even in
that case are you—would you say that it's a problem? והאיכא רוכלין
המחזרין בעיירות. Veha'ika rochlin hamachzirin ba'ayarot.
We know that there would be merchants, spice merchants who are returning
in the towns. spice merchants or perfume merchants that would go from
city to city and presumably these were Jewish merchants. And therefore even
in a city that was completely non-Jewish, there would be Jews that
would drop, you know, that would pass through from time to time.
Now the question is, who cares? I mean, as תוספות Tosfos says,
so some total stranger, non-Jew, passes through and he's supposed to catch
the non-Jew and know what the non-Jew is doing? So that's why
תוספות Tosfos says you see we're talking that it has to be
a case where getting access to the wine makes you look sneaky
and furtive anyway. So therefore we're talking about a case that the
house is locked and sealed and there's a... so you know the
non-Jew sees the non-Jew... they don't care. They assume he's breaking in
and getting the יין נסך. yayin nesech. But any Jew that passes
by, you know, will know that something is up. Even if they're
a total stranger, they'll figure out something is up. Okay, so that's
what the גמרא Gemara says. Why does it matter if you know
why is it a problem even if it's an עיר ir that...
if a city that's fully non-Jews? As long as sometimes Jews drop
by. So אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, בעיר שיש לה דלתים ובריח. b'ir
she'yesh lo dlasayim u'vriach. The city has... is a walled city and
it's sealed at night and no strangers are allowed in. Or if
there are strangers, everybody knows who the strangers are. So people know
to be careful during those times and that's why. But what you
see is that any even slight presence is enough in this case
where according to תוספות Tosfos the house is locked and sealed. Okay.
אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, וחלון כרשות הרבים דמי. v'chalon k'reshus
harabbim dami. Let's say you don't have... it's not exposed to the
public street, but the window from a Jew's house, he has a
line of sight to that house. So there's an extra neighbor that
has a line of sight that's Jewish. That's good enough, even if
it's not a רשות הרבים reshus harabbim as long as the next-door
neighbor is Jewish. ואשפה כרשות הרבים דמי. v'ashpah k'reshus harabbim dami. Not
only that, let's say it's a junkyard. So apparently people would every
periodically go to the junkyard to you know forage around for good
usable junk and or to empty their garbage there. So even though
it's not a public domain, as long as periodically people are found
and they pass by the house, that's good enough.
ודיקלא כרשות הרבים דמי. v'dikla k'reshus harabbim dami. And a palm tree
is like רשות הרבים reshus harabbim because you climb up your palm
tree to get the dates and it gives you a good line
of sight and people will always be afraid about trying to sneak
into a house knowing that people might see him. So the גמרא
Gemara says, פסיק רישיה, psik reisha, let's say the top of the
palm tree is cut off and there are no longer any dates.
Okay? So that... will that still prevent people? So פליגי בה רב
אחא ורבינא. peligi bah Rav Acha v'Ravina. It's a debate. חד אסר,
chad assar, one says it's forbidden, וחד שרי, v'chad sharei, one says
it's permissible. מאן דאסר, man d'assar, the one who says it's forbidden
says nobody... why would he be afraid of that? למאי לסליק התם?
lemai l'isalik hasam? Why would anybody go up on the palm tree?
So therefore he's not afraid that there's a nearby palm tree. ומאן
דשרי, u'man d'sharei, the one that says it's permissible says
no, זימנין דאבדה ליה בהמה, zimnin d'avda leh beheima, sometimes somebody will
have lost an animal,
וסליק, v'salik, and you'll go up on a palm tree, which is
like the top of a telephone pole, gives you a great you
know view of the
neighborhood, לעיוני בתרה, l'iyunei basrah, to try to find your lost animal
that's wandered around. So if there's a palm tree around, maybe that's
enough. So again, תוספות's Tosfos point of all of this is that
because of the slight possibility that somebody might see you, somebody's going
to go up on a palm tree or you know there's a
רוכלין rochlim that pass by every now and then, all of a
sudden the guy isn't going to go into the house. So obviously
we're talking that there's got to be some other safeguard, which is
why תוספות Tosfos assumes that this first case is that the house
is locked and sealed and the person would be looking you know
sneaky and furtive anyway. So any slight presence of a Jew that
could spot him would be enough to stop him. Okay, so that's
how תוספות Tosfos reads that case. Now let's take a look at
a ברייתא Baraita that sort of lays out the four categories. תניא
רבנן. Tanya Rabbanan.
אחד הלוקח ואחד השוכר בית בחצר של עובדי כוכבים, echad halokeach v'echad
hasoker bayis b'chatzer shel ovdei kochavim, whether one purchases or rents a
house in the... in a yard of the עובדי כוכבים. ovdei kochavim.
So but now the house is even owned by the Jew. ומלאו
יין, u'milo'o yayin, and fills it with wine. Now this could be
wine... now this is why again argues to the fact that they're
not really distinct categories. It's all just a question of the likelihood
that you know the non-Jew will want to touch it and touch
it. So here it's totally owned... the wine is totally owned by
the Jew. The house is owned by the Jew. But it's in
a courtyard of non-Jews. So we're just... the only real issue here
is not that it started as non-Jewish wine, the only real issue
is that a non-Jew might have easier access to it. Okay. And
you fill this house with wine, וישראל דר באותו חצר, v'Yisrael dar
b'oso chatzer, but Jews also happen... or that Jew or a Jew
lives also in that yard in that courtyard. מותר, mutar, that's permissible.
Because you know the Jew... other Jews are around and they'll see
this guy trying to get into this house. ואף על פי שאין
מפתח וחותם בידו. v'af al pi she'ein mafteach v'chosam b'yado.
And here even if the house is not locked and sealed. Okay.
So even if it's not locked and sealed, it's very different because
the case of the משנה, Mishnah, who owned the house? The non-Jew.
And whose wine were you dealing with? The non-Jew's. So in that
case, he owns the house and it's his wine, unless... is locked
and sealed. He's going to feel very comfortable going into the house
and doing something with the wine. But this case where you own
the house or are renting it and you own the wine, so
there you don't need the מפתח וחותם, mifte'ach vachotam, but you need
another Jew in the vicinity to make sure, but that's enough. Okay?
Right.
So we're going to deal with some of the cases we have
here right now. בחצר אחרת, bechatzer acheret, let's say there are no
Jews in that courtyard, but in neighboring courtyards, מותר, mutar, it would
be permissible, but only אם הוא שהמפתח וחותם בידו, im hu shehamifte'ach
vachotam beyado, only if you have the lock and seal to the
house. Okay? So if it's your wine and your house, then what
do you need? Either a Jew in the vicinity or the house
needs to be locked and sealed. Okay, that's your wine and your
house. Okay, the non-Jew's wine, the non-Jew's house was the משנה. Mishna.
All right, let's see the rest of this ברייתא. Baraita. יינו של
עובדי כוכבים ברשותו, yeino shel ovdei kochavim b'reshuto, the wine is the
non-Jew's and it's in the non-Jew's house,
וישראל דר באותו חצר, veYisrael dar be'oto chatzer, מותר. mutar. So there
it's the non-Jew's wine, the non-Jew's house,
but a Jew lives in that courtyard. That's permissible, והוא שהמפתח וחותם
בידו, vehu shemifte'ach vachotam beyado, but that again needs it to be
locked and sealed. That's like the case of our משנה. Mishna. You're
going to be tested on all these cases at the end. Okay,
so אמר ליה amar lei רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan לתנא, l'tana, רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said to the תנא, Tanna, no, no, no, תני
אף על פי שאין מפתח וחותם בידו, tani af al pi she'ein
mifte'ach vachotam beyado, מותר. mutar. You in that case, if the Jew
actually lives in the courtyard as opposed to the case of the
משנה Mishna where it was a רשות הרבים reshus harabim and people
were just occasionally passing by, here if the Jew lives in the
courtyard and there's a constant presence, you don't even need the house
to be locked and sealed. The non-Jew's house would be locked? Correct.
You don't even need it to be locked and sealed and the
key held by the Jew. Okay, yeah, right, the key held by
the Jew. Okay,
and בחצר אחרת, bechatzer acheret, if the Jew is in another courtyard,
אסור, asur, and again there's no רשות הרבים reshus harabim and whatnot,
no people dropping by or any of that, אף על פי שמפתח
וחותם בידו, af al pi shemifte'ach vachotam beyado, דברי רבי מאיר. divrei
Rabbi Meir. Then it's forbidden even if it's locked and sealed. וחכמים
אוסרים, vachachamim osrim, and the Rabbis forbid it, עד שיהא שומר יושב
ומשמר, ad sheyeih shomer yoshev umishammer, until you're sitting and watching, או
עד שיבוא ממונה הבא לקטעים, o ad sheyavo memunah habal kiti'in, or
until the sort of person that checks up on people who comes
at appointed times, you know, unless you have that case, if somebody's
dropping in at appointed times. Now the גמרא Gemara is going to
figure out the last point of the חכמים, Chachamim, but let's try
to a little bit organize it. You're right, you know, you don't
have, as James was suggesting, some of the middle cases, which is
the non-Jew owns the house but it's the Jew's wine, or the
Jew owns the house but it's the non-Jew's wine. You really only
have the extreme cases. Okay, so the Jew owns the house and
it's the Jew's wine, basically if there's a Jew in the courtyard
or even a Jew in the neighboring courtyard, if you know then
whatever, it's a lot easier. If the Jew's in the courtyard you
don't need it locked and sealed, Jew in the neighboring courtyard you
do need it locked and sealed. If the non-Jew, if it's the
non-Jew's wine and the non-Jew's house,
right, so that's the case of our משנה. Mishna. So our משנה
Mishna needed it locked and sealed and a רשות הרבים, reshus harabim,
and the ברייתא Baraita here speaks where it's not a רשות הרבים.
reshus harabim. So if it's not a רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, what
you have there, if it's there, the best you could do is
if a Jew lives in the courtyard. Then that might be okay,
maybe you wouldn't even need it locked and sealed. So a lot
of details, I'm sure it's hard to keep them all straight. Anyway,
let's see what the גמרא Gemara does with this. Okay,
okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, what?
חכמים Chachamim answering to the last?
So that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to ask. רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says in the last case, right,
it's אסור asur if he's in another courtyard, it's אסור asur even
if it's locked and sealed. So what do the Rabbis mean when
they say it's אסור asur unless somebody is שומר? shomer? It sounds
like they're responding to somebody who was lenient, but רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir himself just said it was אסור. asur. So let's take a
look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, חכמים אהיי, Chachamim a-hai,
which case are the חכמים Chachamim responding to? אילימא אסיפא, ileima aseifa,
the last case, which is when it's the wine and the house
of the non-Jew and the Jew is in another courtyard, so in
that case תנא קמא נמי מיסר קאסר. tanna kama nami misar ka'asar.
So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir also said it was forbidden, right? Even
locked and sealed doesn't work in that case.
ואלא רישא דסיפא, ve-ela reisha de-seifa, the first half of the last
two cases, where it's the wine and the house of the non-Jew
but the Jew is in the courtyard.
So there, maybe the Rabbis are saying, oh, in the courtyard you
think it's מותר, mutar, we're going to tell you it's אסור asur
and you need a constant שומר. shomer. But והא קאמר ליה v'ha
ka-amar lei רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan לתנא, l'tana, but רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan told the תנא, Tanna, תני אף על פי שאין מפתח וחותם
בידו. tani af al pi she'ein mifte'ach vachotam beyado. That if the
Jew lives regularly in the courtyard, not just passerby, that even if
it's the house and the wine of the non-Jew, it's okay even
if it's not locked and sealed. So you see רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan is so inclined to be lenient when a Jew is living
in the courtyard, it's hard to imagine that the Rabbis would be
responding. responding and saying, oh no, you need a regular שומר shomer
in that case. Now again, it's a little strange, you know, maybe
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is just פסקנינג paskening leniently, but the חכמים
Chachamim here are strict. But the גמרא Gemara doesn't accept that. So
the last again, I know it's hard to keep the details straight,
but the last two cases are versions of the wine in the
house of the non-Jew and so there when... wait a minute... when
the non-Jew is not in the courtyard, we're very strict, so you
don't need the חכמים Chachamim here to be strict because we're already
strict. When it's in the courtyard, the attitude of רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan is to be very lenient, even if it's not מפתח וחותם.
mufteach ve-chosem. So it's hard to imagine in that case that we're
going to have the חכמים Chachamim being strict and needing a שומר,
shomer, a guard. What? I know. It doesn't... why? Maybe רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan is lenient but the חכמים Chachamim are strict. I don't
know. Okay, but that's what רשי Rashi just says is if you
see our inclination is to interpret that case leniently if a Jew
is living in the courtyard, we wouldn't want to interpret the חכמים
Chachamim on that last case. So let's keep on going.
אלא, Ella, the גמרא Gemara says, הסיפא דרישא, a seifa de-reisha, the
second half of the first case. The first case is it's all
owned by the Jew, the wine and the house. So we said
there that if it's in a neighboring courtyard, it's enough if it's
locked and sealed. Okay, then it's אסור assur unless it's locked and
sealed. So the גמרא Gemara says דקאמר תנא קמא, de-kama tana kama,
so the תנא קמא Tana Kama is saying, בחצר אחרת מותר be-chatzer
acheres mutar if he's in the neighboring courtyard it's permissible, והוא שמפתח
וחותם בידו, ve-hu she-mufteach ve-chosem be-yado, if it's locked and sealed and
he has the key. וחכמים אומרים Ve-chachamim omrim even that's not enough
if it's not exposed to רשות הרבים reshus ha-rabim and the guy
is in the other courtyard, then nobody is watching him because he
can do what he needs to do without anybody seeing him, right?
And there's no street that runs by it, the only other person
who would see him and cares is in the other courtyard. So
it's not a problem. So in that case לעולם אסור עד ששומר
יושב ומשמר. le-olam assur ad she-shomer yoshev u-mishameir. So their case you
need somebody present in the courtyard, או עד שיבוא ממונה הבא לקיטין,
o ad she-yavo memuneh ha-ba le-kitin,
or you have somebody that comes at a point of time to
check up even if he's not regularly sitting there. So the גמרא
Gemara finally asks, who cares that it's regular, I mean regular times
makes it worse. The גמרא Gemara says בא לקיטין גריעותא הוא, ba
le-kitin gireusa hu, if you know like okay there's going to be
a surprise inspection at ten o'clock, okay? It doesn't do any good,
right? So the coming at fixed times you know when to be
on your best behavior. So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא עד שיבוא
ממונה שאינו בא לקיטין. ella ad she-yavo memuneh she-eino ba le-kitin. Okay,
so shifts the context a little. It means unless somebody comes who
comes without appointed times and makes surprise inspections. All right, so a
lot of different cases based on you know how comfortable this person
feels, it's my house, it's my wine, is there anybody who might
pass by, who lives here, or no, no street that passes by,
they're only in the other courtyard, and all of these are to
figure out the likelihood, which is why, although as a formalist I'm
attracted to the approach of רשי Rashi and the רמבם Rambam that
so to say there's a fundamental difference between if it starts by
the Jew or starts by the non-Jew, you define how do you
define the wine, this really makes it sound like there's no fundamental
difference. Like the whole question is what is the likelihood it was
touched, but when it's in the under the control, you know, in
the property and it's owned by the non-Jew, then obviously the likelihood
is a lot greater so you need more safeguards. And that seems
to be that we're not making any categorical distinction, just talking about
the degrees of likelihood. Okay, so let's now take a look at
the last case, רבן שמעון בן אלעזר אומר רשות עובדי כוכבים אחת
היא. Rabban Shimon ben Elazar Omer reshus ovdei kochavim achas hi. So
this was going the first case of the משנה, Mishnah, where there
was a... that a... or no, I'm sorry, this is going yeah,
the first case of the משנה, Mishnah, where there was a street
that passed by the house, it was the house and the wine
were the non-Jew's, but the Jew, according to again according to תוספות
Tosafot it was under lock and seal, and רבן שמעון בן אלעזר
Rabban Shimon ben Elazar says this very cryptic statement: it's all one.
What does that mean it's all one? So let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. איבעיא להו, Iba’ya lehu, רבן שמעון בן אלעזר
להקל או להחמיר, Rabban Shimon ben Elazar le-hakel o le-hachmir, is he
being lenient or is he being strict? It'd first be nice to
know what he's saying. So, but we'll give two interpretations of what
he's saying. רב יהודה אמר זעירי להקל, Rav Yehuda amar Ze'iri le-hakel,
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda in the name of זעירי Ze'iri says he's
being lenient, רב נחמן אמר זעירי להחמיר, Rav Nachman amar Ze'iri le-hachmir,
and רב נחמן Rav Nachman in the name of זעירי Ze'iri says
he's being strict. רב יהודה אמר זעירי להקל והכי קאמר. Rav Yehuda
amar Ze'iri le-hakel ve-hachi kamar. This is what he's saying. והכי קאמר
תנא קמא. Ve-hachi kamar Tana Kama. So the first opinion
saying: כשם שברשותו אסור, keshem she-bi-reshuso assur, the same way when it's
in again the wine, as Gabe said, there are cases we're not
talking about. We're not talking about Jewish wine in a non-Jewish house,
or non-Jew's wine in the Jew's house. Okay, but we are going
to talk about, but here the גמרא Gemara is going to talk
about one variation. The wine is owned by the non-Jew and it's
being stored in a non-Jew's house but a different non-Jew. So does
that make it better because now, you know, the non-Jew who owns
it, he's the one that feels he's the בעל הבית, ba'al ha-bayis,
he's entitled, but maybe if he has to now go into a
different person's house, even a different non-Jew's house, maybe that would be
a different story. Okay. והכי
קאמר תנא קמא כשם שברשותו אסור, Ve-hachi kamar Tana Kama: keshem she-bi-reshuso
assur, the same way in the רשות reshus of a non-Jew it's
forbidden unless with the safeguards
mentioned, כך ברשות עובד כוכבים אחר נמי אסור, kach bi-reshus oved kochavim
acher nami assur, similarly when it's in the domain of another non-Jew.
of another non-Jew you need the same type of precautions, וחיישינן לגומלין.
vechaishinan legomlin. We are concerned for reciprocity. גומלין Gomlin is you scratch
my back, I scratch your back. So, are we concerned that the
non-Jew goes to his non-Jew friend and says, look, I know the
Jew gave you this wine to watch, but you know, if you
let me get access to it now and do a little sprinkling
to my עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, next time it happens to you
and you're keeping wine by my house, I'll return the favor. So,
I'm not saying they're actually explicitly saying this, right, exactly, they're explicitly
saying this, but it's like there's an understanding. We're very, we're very,
you know, sort of laissez-faire when it comes to our friend non-Jews
wanting access to wine in order to sprinkle it to עבודה זרה.
avodah zarah. Okay, so that's one approach. So even if it's in
a, it's like almost, did anybody see this classic Saturday Night Live
with Eddie Murphy? He wants to see how white people act when
no black people are around, and he gets somebody like to paint
his face like he's a white person and goes into a bank
and he asks for a loan and you know, the bank officer
looks around and he sees like there's no black people and says,
here, just take our money! You know, so it's like, you know,
so it's like this whole how they act when nobody else is
watching.
Okay, so
is it that deep or is it just that since they're both
עובדי כוכבים, ovdei kochavim, that's
the point, you know,
it's not at his house, it's not a big deal.
Yes, but not just not a big deal, can have access to
wine that you're watching for the Jew. Oh, what do I care?
We all know it's all for עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. We all
know we go easy on, you know, when things are for our
gods we don't, you know, we're just all friends, right? It's all
בינינו. beineinu.
So that's okay. So וחיישינן לגומלין. vechaishinan legomlin. Okay, so we're concerned
about that. So even if it's in another person's home and he
normally would be given the responsibility of watching it, we're afraid that
they'll just be very laissez-faire with one another and therefore you need
the same precautions. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar
omer, and רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar says back,
במה דברים אמורים bameh devarim amurim ברשותו, bireshuto,
when is it you need all the precautions? When it's in the
owner's possession, in his house.
אבל ברשות עובד כוכבים אחר, aval bireshus oved kochavim acher, so מותר,
mutar, it's permissible, you don't need those precautions, ולא חיישינן לגומלין, velo
chaishinan legomlin, we're not concerned about reciprocity and a sort of exchanging
of favors. Okay, and the way to read the phrase is ברשות
עובד כוכבים אחת היא? bireshus oved kochavim achas hi? Are you treating
all non-Jews' domain as one? Meaning, just because it's a non-Jew, not
all, it's not the same, it's a different person's domain, and that's
enough to say that you're not afraid that the guy's just going
to waltz in and use it. Okay? It's under somebody else's protection.
That's one way of reading it. And the other way is just
flipping it.
One minute. Okay,
that's one. ולא חיישינן. Velo chaishinan. רב נחמן אמר זירי להחמיר, Rav
Nachman amar Zeiri lehachmir, he's being strict. והכי קאמר תנא קמא, Vehachi
ka'amar tanna kamma, the תנא קמא tanna kamma is the one being
lenient. במה דברים אמורים Bameh devarim amurim ברשותו, bireshuto, when do you
need those precautions? When it's in his domain. אבל ברשות עובד כוכבים
אחר, Aval bireshus oved kochavim acher, if it's in another non-Jew's domain,
מותר, mutar, it's permissible, ולא חיישינן לגומלין, velo chaishinan legomlin,
and we are not concerned for reciprocity. So it's only when it's
in his domain are we concerned he'll take too much license. רבי
שמעון בן אלעזר אומר, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer, כל רשות עובד
כוכבים אחת היא. kol reshus oved kochavim achas hi. He's being strict,
he says, no, he doesn't say it like, do you think it's
all one? He's saying it is all one. Any non-Jew, it's all
basically the same, they'll do each other favors, and it's a problem.
So the good thing about all this is that we פוסקין poskin
the lenient way, which is not only good in the sense that
it makes it more lenient, but also that it's right, does not
create such a conspiracy theory about non-Jews. Understand, you're entering into a
business relationship with this non-Jew and he's supposed to watch your wine
that you trust him. And the only case that you're concerned about
is is if it's, you know, the the wine of the non-Jew
and his house, so it's all his, that he that case he
feels too much license regarding it. Okay.
Where are we? במה דברים אמורים ברשותו ברשות עובד כוכבים אחר מותר
ולא חיישינן. Bameh devarim amurim bireshuto bireshus oved kochavim acher mutar velo
chaishinan. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר כל רשות עובד כוכבים אחת היא
ולא חיישינן לגומלין. Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer kol reshus oved kochavim
achas hi velo chaishinan legomlin. Did I skip a line? Yeah, and
he says it's all one and he's strict. אחת היא. Achas hi.
תניא כוותיה דרב נחמן אמר זירי להחמיר. Tanya kevasieh deRav Nachman amar
Zeiri lehachmir. We taught like רב נחמן Rav Nachman and זירי Zeiri
that that רבי שמעון בן אלעזר's Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar being strict.
But that's good, that means the תנא קמא, tanna kamma, which is
the majority opinion, is being lenient. What's the ברייתא? braita? אמר רבי
שמעון בן אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar, כל רשות עובד כוכבים
אחת היא, kol reshus oved kochavim achas hi, it's all treated as
one, מפני הרמאין, mipnei harama'in, because of the people that are devious,
that trick. So we can't trust them and we treat it all
as one domain. Okay. So the protocols of the elders of Zeus
or something. Okay, fine. דבי פרזיק רופילא, Debei Parzik Rufla, so in
the house of פרזיק רופילא, Parzik Rufla, פרזיק Parzik is a person's
name apparently, and רופילא Rufla is a like a second to the
king, so it's a very important person. So he was a non-Jew.
אותיבו חמרא גבי אריסיהו. Otivu chamra gabei arisaihu. So he had somebody
was working his vineyards, a Jew, and deposited the wine by this
non-Jew's sharecropper. Okay, not by the non-Jew itself, so it's a different
domain, it's not the same, but it is somebody that's subservient to
him. All right, so let's take a look. סבר רבנן קמיה... Savar
rabanan kamei... דרבה למימר, de-Rava le-meimar, so the Rabbis who were sitting
in front of Rava thought to say כי חיישינן לגומלים, ki hashinan
le-gomlim, when would we be concerned about reciprocity and favors? הני מילי
היכא דקא מוסיף האי גבי האי. hani milei heicha de-ka mosif hai
gabi hai. That's when each one, when there would be equal people,
I do you a favor, you do me a favor. אבל הכא
aval hacha here, כיון דאריסא kivan de-arisa it's a sharecropper, he's not
going to ever ask, you know, this general or this, you know,
second to the king to hey, let me store some wine by
your
house.
So there will never be
an exchange
of
favors. It's a, you know, it's unequal social status and power. So
there's no reason to be concerned I'm going to do him a
favor because he'll do me a favor. He never does me any
favors.
So therefore it's not a concern. So אמר להו רבא, amar lehu
Rava, so Rava said back to them אדרבה, aderaba, the opposite. אפילו
מאן דאמר לא חיישינן לגומלים, afilu man de-amar lo hashinan le-gomlim, even
if we say we're not normally concerned about exchange of favors, הני
מילי היכא דלא מירתת מיניה, hani milei heicha de-lo mirsas minei, that's
when they're of equal social status, so I'm not afraid of you,
I'm not subservient to you, I'm not going to, you know, compromise
my integrity, you know, and in order to, you know, just to
do you a favor. אבל הכא כיון דמירתת מיניה, aval hacha kivan
de-mirsas minei, it's a sharecropper which is subservient to him מחפיא ליה
זכותיה, machpia leh zechuteh, he tries to cover up for him. So
even if we're normally not afraid that people will do favors and
act in ways they shouldn't act, here somebody's subservient, we are afraid
that they'll cover up for their superior. Okay, and now the Gemara
ends ההוא כרכא, hahu karcha, there was a city דהוה יתיב בי
חמרא דישראל, de-hava yasiv be chamra de-Yisrael, that there was Jewish wine
in it, it's like in some barrels in a street. אישתכח עובד
כוכבים דהוה קאי בי דני, ishtakach oved kochavim de-hava kai be danei,
and there was a non-Jew found between the pitchers. So, you know,
and there's a question, was he touching the wine? So אמר רבא,
amar Rava, if נתפס עליו כגנב, nitpas alav ke-ganav, if it's a
type of a city where had he, you know, been seen with
the wine he would have gotten in trouble. נתפס עליו כגנב nitpas
alav ke-ganav means he would have been seized like a thief. So
if he was seen as doing something wrong, the police would have
got, he would have got in some trouble. So if that's the
case חמרא שרי, chamra sharei, the wine is permissible, because we can
assume that he's not going to do it if he'll, you know,
if he'll get in trouble if he's seen fiddling around with barrels
that aren't his. ואי לא אסור, ve-ei lo assur, but if it's
a type of a city where he could do it and he
would get away with it, then it's not a problem. That's similar
to, analogous to, you know, the non-Jew breaking into his house, you
know, and are there people that are going to catch him, not
going to catch him, is he afraid he'll be seen, get in
trouble, not get in trouble? So here it's exactly analogous, which again
shows that we're really not looking at Jewish wine versus not Jewish
wine categorically differently. It's all the question about how much license the
person thinks he has, how much liberty he's inclined to take, and
what type of safeguards there are to ensure that it is not
being touched. Okay, so with that we finished this Perek הדרן עלך
רבי ישמעאל. Hadran alach Rabbi Yishmael. I should say before you just
close your Gemara just a minute, that very uncharacteristically of Rashi at
the very end, after you see it says הדרן עלך רבי ישמעאל,
Hadran alach Rabbi Yishmael, there's a little thing, it actually says that
it's written not by Rashi but by Rashi's students, that tries to
sort of almost give you the rules that emerge from this, because
there were so many millions of cases of what type of touch
that like, okay, what are the rules at the end? I just
want to read you a little section just that you get like
a sense of the flavor of it, okay, about how they try,
even Rashi already who's not a codifier is trying to systematize the
rules. Okay, so look what he says. מסקנא דמילתא, maskana de-milta, the
bottom line is, you see like this paragraph at the end, מגע
עובד כוכבים כיון דנתכוין ליגע שיכשך, maga oved kochavim kivan de-nitkaven liga
she-shichshach, so if he's intending to touch and he moves his hand
around, אף על פי שלא נצק, af al pi she-lo nizak, although
he didn't sort of point it, אסור בהנאה. assur be-hana'ah. And we
know that from the case of אגרא דמן עובדי כוכבים משום לך
לך אמרין לנזירא. Agra de-min ovdei kochavim mishum lech lech amrin le-nezira.
Okay, so whatever, we know it from case number one. שלא בכוונה,
she-lo be-chavana, if he's touching it without intent, כגון שלא הכיר בו
שהוא יין, kegon she-lo hikkir bo she-hu yayin, he doesn't even know
it's wine, מותר בהנאה, mutar be-hana'ah, then it is permissible in hana'ah.
ממתיניתין, mi-matnitin, it goes through all the cases. Direct touch, not direct
touch, kocho, kavanah, not kavanah, is it mutar be-hana'ah, is it mutar
be-shtiyah? So very uncharacteristic, but again this is the nature of this
Perek, that it did not really clarify the rules so well and
you have to try to pull it all together. And then at
the very end he just says like this. כך הגיע, kach higgia,
the last five words הרב, ha-Rav, which is Rashi, ופסק הלכה למעשה.
u-pasak halacha le-ma'aseh. Okay, so this is how Rashi sort of what
Rashi used as his psak halacha. Obviously what Rashi's conclusions will be
is not what all the Rishonim's conclusions will be, but this actually
is the upshot. And I'll just end because with one more case
here, practical case, of the question about a non-Jew transporting wine. Tosafot
wanted to know, you've made wine, you send it with a non-Jew
to sell in a different city, when he's going with that wine,
why isn't that like the case of, you know, nobody else is
around and he's not afraid of being caught and why isn't it
a concern? So Tosafot basically has to say there's a big difference.
In the case in the משנה, Mishnah, the non-Jew did no effort,
so he's not really afraid of consequences so much. But if he's
transporting the wine and he's going to sell it and make a
profit, he's really afraid of what would be the consequences if he's
caught da-da-da-da-da, and therefore, you know, and then he loses all his
profit, so there we're not concerned. So another attempt to sort of
bring this משנה Mishnah into a practical application. Okay, we will continue
tomorrow with a new פרק, Perek, which although it continues to talk
about יין נסך, Yayin Nesech, is not as complicated as this with
all of the different ways of plugging and all of the details.
Okay.